Guide to the Collection of Film Material Relating to John Steinbeck
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Collection of Film Material Relating to John Steinbeck
1933-1993
YCAL MSS 1191
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.29
3 boxes + 9 broadsides
Collection of photographs and printed materials relating chiefly to film and television productions of work by John Steinbeck.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Royal Book on various funds, 2015-2016.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Photographs, 1939-1982. II. Printed and Other Material, 1938-1993.
John Steinbeck (1902-1968)
John Steinbeck, born 27 February 1902 in Salinas, California, was an American author and novelist, best known for his novel, The Grapes of Wrath (1939), which was awarded a Pulitzer Prize and National Book Award in 1940. Steinbeck received the Nobel Prize for Literature for 1962. He died 20 December 1968 in New York.
Scope and Contents
Collection of photographs and printed materials relating chiefly to film and television productions of work by John Steinbeck.
Steinbeck wrote the scripts for the film versions of his stories The Pearl (1948) and The Red Pony (1949), and he wrote the script directly for Viva Zapata! (1952).
Photographs include studio publicity and reference prints for productions of East of Eden, A medal for Benny, Of mice and men, The pearl, The red pony, Tortilla flat, Viva Zapata!, and The wayward bus, as well as Rogers and Hammerstein's stage production of Pipe dream (adapted from Sweet Thursday ). Photographs include Marlon Brando, Lon Chaney, Jr., Joan Collins, James Dean, Dorothy Lamour, Myrna Loy, Jayne Mansfield, Burgess Meredith, Robert Mitchum, and Spencer Tracy.
Printed materials include film posters, lobby cards, and pressbooks. Titles include: Burning bright, Cannery row, East of Eden, A medal for Benny, The moon is down, Of mice and men, The pearl, The red pony, Tortilla flat, Viva Zapata!, and The wayward bus. With shooting script for Tortilla flat.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Motion pictures -- United States; Screenwriters -- United States -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Screenwriters -- United States -- 20th Century; Brando, Marlon, 1924-2004; Chaney, Lon, Jr., 1906-1973; Collins, Joan, 1933-; Dean, James, 1931-1955; Hammerstein, Oscar, II, 1895-1960; Lamour, Dorothy, 1914-1996; Loy, Myrna, 1905-1993; Mansfield, Jayne, 1933-1967; Meredith, Burgess, 1907-1997; Mitchum, Robert; Rodgers, Richard, 1902-1979; Steinbeck, John, 1902-1968; Tracy, Spencer, 1900-1967
- Photographs, 1939-1982; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Scope and Contents
  Photographs in the collection include studio publicity and reference prints for productions of East of Eden, A medal for Benny, Of mice and men, The pearl, The red pony, Tortilla flat, Viva Zapata!, and The wayward bus, as well as Rogers and Hammerstein's stage production of Pipe dream (adapted from Sweet Thursday ).
  Photographs include actors Marlon Brando, Lon Chaney, Jr., Joan Collins, James Dean, Dorothy Lamour, Myrna Loy, Jayne Mansfield, Burgess Meredith, Robert Mitchum, and Spencer Tracy.
  - East of Eden, circa 1955 (Box 1)
  - A medal for Benny, circa 1945 (Box 1)
  - Of mice and men, circa 1939 (Box 1)
  - The pearl, circa 1948 (Box 1)
  - The red pony, circa 1949 (Box 1)
  - Sweet Thursday, adapted as "Pipe dreams", 1955 (Box 1)
  - Tortilla flat, 1942, undated (Box 1)
  - Viva Zapata!", circa 1951 (Box 1)
  - Viva Zapata!, circa 1951 (Box 3)
  - The wayward bus, circa 1957 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, [1982?] (Box 1)
- Printed and Other Material, 1938-1993; 1.88; (2 boxes) + 9 broadsides
  Printed materials in the collection include film posters, lobby cards, and pressbooks. Titles includee following titles: Burning bright, Cannery row, East of Eden, A medal for Benny, The moon is down, Of mice and men, The pearl, The red pony, Tortilla flat, Viva Zapata!, and The wayward bus.
  With shooting script for Tortilla flat.
  - Burning bright, 1989, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Cannery row, circa 1982 (Box 3)
  - Cannery row, circa 1982 (Box 4 (Broadside))
  - East of Eden, 1967-1968, undated (Box 2)
  - East of Eden, circa 1955 (Box 3)
  - East of Eden, circa 1955 (Box 5 (Broadside))
  - Flight, [1961?] (Box 2)
  - The grapes of wrath, 1989 (Box 2)
  - A medal for Benny, circa 1945 (Box 3)
  - A medal for Benny, circa 1945 (Box 6 (Broadside))
  - The moon is down, circa 1943 (Box 7 (Broadside))
  - Of mice and men, 1938-1975, undated (Box 2)
  - Of mice and men, circa 1939, circa 1992 (Box 3)
  - Of mice and men, circa 1939, circa 1992 (Box 8 (Broadside))
  - The pearl, circa 1945 (Box 3)
  - The pearl, circa 1945 (Box 9 (Broadside))
  - The red pony, circa 1949, circa 1973 (Box 3)
  - The red pony, circa 1949, circa 1973 (Box 10 (Broadside))
  - Sweet Thursday, 1955- (Box 2)
  - Tortilla flat, shooting script, typescript mimeograph, annotated, 1941 July 16 (Box 2)
  - Tortilla flat, circa 1942 (Box 3)
  - Tortilla flat, circa 1942 (Box 11 (Broadside))
  - Viva Zapata!, circa 1952 (Box 2)
  - Viva Zapata!, circa 1952 (Box 3)
  - The wayward bus, circa 1957 (Box 3)
  - The wayward bus, circa 1957 (Box 12 (Broadside))